William A. Benney Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William A. Benney Papers 1909-1966 (bulk 1920-1931)
MSS85320
Benney, William A.
1,250 items
3 containers plus 1 oversize
1.0 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Research superintendent. Notes, correspondence, drawings, lists, payroll records, newspaper clippings, personal papers, printed matter, and photographs largely documenting Benney’s employment by Thomas A. Edison, centering on the work carried out in Fort Myers, Florida, to find a substitute for natural rubber.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Benney, William A.; Edison, Charles A., 1890-1969.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931.
Subjects
Machine design.; Research, Industrial--Florida--Fort Myers.; Rubber, Artificial.; Tools--Design and construction.
Occupations
Research superintendents.
Provenance
The papers of William A. Benney, research superintendent, were purchased by the Library of Congress in 2004.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William A. Benney are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William A. Benney (1885-1965) span the years 1909-1966, with the bulk of the material dating from 1920 to 1931, and consist of notes, correspondence, drawings, lists, payroll records, newspaper clippings, personal papers, printed matter, and photographs documenting his employment by Thomas A. Edison as a research superintendent. Scrapbooks, containing approximately four hundred notes written between Benney, Thomas A. Edison, Charles A. Edison, as well as others, document day-to-day laboratory activities especially during the search for a natural rubber substitute carried out at Edison’s winter home in Fort Myers, Florida. Included also in the scrapbooks are correspondence and drawings of machinery and tools. The payroll records, signed by Benney, document work conducted by carpenters and laborers on the Edison property in Fort Myers. There are also equipment lists. Newspaper clippings largely pertain to Thomas A. Edison, but also cover Benney’s personal life. Other items of a personal nature include correspondence, invitations, Benney’s death certificate, and a rental agreement for a store in Morris Township, New Jersey. The printed matter consists mostly of memorabilia pertaining to Thomas A. Edison. Photographs include portraits inscribed to Benney by Thomas A. Edison and Charles A. Edison. The three photograph albums document the Edison estate and laboratory in Fort Myers and the Benney family.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by subject or type of material.
Container List
- Lists of equipment, 1927, undated (Box 1)
- Miscellany, undated (Box 1)
- Newspaper clippings, 1922-1939, undated (Box 1)
- Payroll records, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
- Personal papers, 1920-1936, 1965-1966, undated (Box 1)
- Photograph albums (Box 1)
  - Vol. 1, 1909-1957, undated (Box 1)
  - Vol. 2, circa 1920-circa1931 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 3, 1928-1929, undated (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1922, 1933, 1945, 1958, undated (Box 2)
- Printed matter, 1925-1933, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks (Box 2)
  - Vols. 1-4, 1920-1931, undated See also Oversize, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Vol. 5, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Scrapbooks (Box OV 1)
    - Vol. 4 (Box OV 1)
      - Note, 1928, Apr. 20 (Container 2) (Box OV 1)